Finding Aid for Department of Psychology (University of Michigan) records, 1903-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Psychology (University of Michigan) records
1903-1998
1960-1990
University of Michigan. Department of Psychology.
10.25 linear feet in 10 boxes
437 KB online
87162 Bimu C26 2
Teaching and research unit of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts of the University of Michigan. Records include administrative files, committee minutes, reports, some course material and a topical file which contains some information on student antiwar activities, 1966-1967. Also several photos of the psychology laboratories, 1903-1915.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Transferred by the Department of Psychology beginning in 1976 (Donor No. 5883 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The Department of Psychology records are open for research except for certain student related records restricted by statute or university policy.
The Department of Psychology record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 5
Psychology as a separate course of study was not recognized in the United States until the last quarter of the nineteenth century. At the University of Michigan, the Department of Psychology was officially formed in 1929, but instruction in psychology or "Mental Philosophy" as it was called, was available from the Department of Philosophy from 1852. Many prominent figures in early American psychology taught at the University of Michigan. President Tappan, who was Professor of Mental Philosophy as well as president of the university, taught courses in mental philosophy from 1852 to 1863. Other important figures include John Dewey who established the first psychological laboratory, and George Herbert Mead and James H. Tufts, who each briefly held positions at the school in the 1890s. Walter Pillsbury, the first professor to be appointed to the newly separated Department of Psychology, revived laboratory psychology in 1898 and headed the department from 1929 to 1942. He built its reputation as an excellent teaching department with a research emphasis on experimental psychology.
The department boomed after World War II as it began to take on its modern attributes: a large staff, many professors engaged in interdisciplinary research, a large number of graduate students, and a nationally ranked program. Much of the credit for this growth and diversification is credited to the work of Donald G. Marquis, Department Chairman from 1945 to 1957.
In the early 1960s the department introduced sub-disciplines to facilitate communication between faculty and students in the huge department. These sub-disciplines also allowed students to specialize within a field of study that was growing more and more diverse. The sub-disciplines grew to include experimental, clinical, community, physiological, mathematical, personality, social, psychobiology (neuroscience), developmental, industrial, and general psychology.
In recent years the growth has slowed, but the national reputation and solid work done in clinical, social, and mathematical psychology endure. The Department of Psychology at this time is one of the largest departments of the university and boasts some of the highest class enrollments at both the undergraduate and graduate levels.
Chairs of the Department of Psychology
1929-1942 Walter Pillsbury
1945-1957 Donald G. Marquis
1958-1961 E. Lowell Kelly
1961-1971 Wilbert J. McKeachie
1971-1976 J. E. Keith Smith
1977-1982 Warren T. Norman
1982-1991 Albert Cain
1992-2001 Patricia Y. Gurin
2002-2007 Richard Gonzalez
2007-2012 Theresa M. Lee
2012- Robert M. Sellers
The records of the University of Michigan Department of Psychology document the department from its beginnings, through a period of rapid growth after World War II, to its present standing as a diverse and well established division of the University of Michigan. The first accession of materials from the department was received in 1990 and consisted of about 5 linear inches. Four linear feet of materials have now been added forming one integrated run of records.
The materials are arranged into eight series: History, Administrative Committees, Budget, Course Materials, Sub-disciplines, Topical Administrative Files, Faculty, and Students.
Subjects:
Graduate students.; Pillsbury, W. B. (Walter Bowers), 1872-1960.; Psychology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975--Protest movements.
Subjects - Visual Material:
University of Michigan. Homoeopathic Hospital.; Photographs.; Psychology Laboratory (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- History, 1903-1986
  The History series (0.5 linear feet, 1936-1986) consists of organizational documents, publications, reports, reviews, and speeches. These materials are especially useful for obtaining a general sense of the department and the conditions and standards under which it functions.
  The publication, reports, and reviews contain summary information on the accomplishments of the department and goals for the future. They document the history of the department and the different directions it has taken. The reviews in particular are a strength of this series, providing frank appraisals of various strengths and weaknesses.
  The State of the Department Speeches, given by Wilbert McKeachie from 1961 to 1970, are perhaps the best sources of summary information. They exemplify the spirit of self-review and analysis that seemed to characterize the administrative life of the department. They also provide insight into the mentality of the department and trends in policy, curriculum, and research during a highly formative decade. All of these materials may be a good beginning for general research even though they are not comprehensive, leaving many time periods and activities unaccounted for.
  Also located within this series are two photographs of the psychology laboratories as they stood from 1903 to 1915.
  - 1903-1986
    - Articles of Organization, 1936; 1946 (Box 1)
    - Audio Tape
      - A. Raphelson, "History of Psychology Department to 1950", 7-inch reel, 3 3/4 ips (Box 1)
    - Photographs, Psychology Laboratory, circa 1903-1910; 2 photographs (Box 1)
    - Publication: "Psychology at Michigan: The Pillsbury Years, 1897-1947", undated (Box 1)
    - Reports
      - "Alternative Administrative Structures for the Department of Psychology,", undated (Box 1)
      - "Report of Administrative Organization,", 1951 (Box 1)
      - "Departmental Statement to the Dean"
        - 1961 (Box 1)
        - 1965 (Box 1)
      - "Regent Fellows Report" (Box 1)
      - "Report of the Program Evaluation Committee for Social Sciences" (Box 1)
    - Reviews
      - Departmental Review (Box 1)
      - 1960-1961
        - (McKeachie), 1965 (Box 1)
        - (Katz), 1970-1971 (Box 1)
      - Five Year Review, June 1981 (Box 1)
    - Speeches
      - State of Department Wilbert McKeachie, 1961-1970 (Box 1)
- Administrative Committees, 2006, 1960-1998
  The Administrative Committees series (3 linear feet, 437 KB (online); 1960-1998 and 2006) includes materials created by the department-wide, policy-making bodies. This is mostly material from the Executive Committee and Staff Meetings although there is also some minimal information created by the Ad Hoc Committee on Departmental Structure and Function, the Committee on Undergraduate Studies, and the Committee on Graduate Studies.
  The Administrative Committees series deals mostly with everyday activities and issues of curriculum, policy, and research as well as faculty and student enrollment, placement, funding, and graduation. The Executive Committee meeting minutes are excellent in that they run from 1960 to 1998 with few chronological gaps. All of the records are organized into two sub-series, 1960-1989 and 1983-1998, 2006; and arranged chronologically under the title of the committee.
  - 1960-1989
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Departmental Structure and Function, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Augmented Executive Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Evaluation, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee
      - Executive Committee Retreat Synopsis, 1969 (Box 1)
      - Minutes
        - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
        - 1967-1969 (Box 1)
        - 1970-1972 (Box 1)
        - 1975-1977 (Box 1)
        - 1980 (Box 1)
        - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
        - 1985 (Box 1)
        - 1986 (Box 1)
        - 1987 (Box 1)
        - 1988 (Box 1)
        - 1989 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Studies Committee, Minutes, November 1, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Psychology Department Review Committee, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Staff Meetings Minutes
      - 1961-1965 (Box 1)
      - 1966-1968 (Box 1)
      - 1969 (Box 1)
      - 1970-1972 (Box 1)
      - 1977-1984 (Box 1)
      - 1985-1989 (Box 1)
    - Undergraduate Studies Committee (Box 2)
      - Minutes, 1969-1988 (Box 2)
      - Undergraduate Education, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - 1983-1998, 2006
    - Executive Committees (Box 6)
      - Area Chair Council Meeting Minutes, September 1994-September 1998 (Box 6)
      - Faculty Meeting Minutes, September 1992-April 1997 (Box 6)
      - Meeting Agendas and Minutes
        - May 1983-May 1985 (Box 6)
        - September 1985-August 1987 (Box 6)
        - September 1987-March 1991 (Box 6)
        - April 1992-April 1993 (Box 6)
        - September 1993-May 1994 (Box 6)
        - November 1997-March 1998 (Box 6)
      - September 1994-May 1995 (Box 7)
      - June 1995-April 1996 (Box 7)
      - September 1996-May 1997 (Box 7)
      - July 1997-April 1998 (Box 7)
      - September 1998 (Box 7)
    - Psychology Graduate Office
      - Requirements, Policies and Procedures Manual, 2005-2006
    - Staff Meetings Process File, 1994-1998 (Box 7)
    - Retreat, 1996 (Box 7)
    - Staff Meetings Process File, 1994-1998 (Box 7)
- Budget, 1970-1988
  The Budget series (0.25 linear feet, 1972-1988) has been retained because of its summary financial information. Some of the materials one might find here are annual total expenditures, percentages of the budget received from the University or outside sources, percentages of the budget used by each sub-discipline on a yearly or 5-year basis, and possible sources of funding for equipment, scholarships, etc. Because the information in this series is extremely varied and offers only fragmentary documentation, it has been arranged in a simple chronological order.
  - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - 1975 (Box 2)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - 1978 (Box 2)
  - 1981, 1988 (Box 2)
- Course Materials, 1926-1977
  The Course Materials series (0.25 linear feet, 1930-1977) documents only a few of the courses offered in the Department of Psychology. Most of the classes represented in this collection are part of the social psychology sub-discipline. Class materials are divided by title and include exams, syllabi, and course outlines. Many of these class materials span a number of years making it apparent to see how specific courses have changed in focus, curriculum, or approach.
  Of special interest in this series are 2 folders of handwritten lecture notes, most likely from Walter Pillsbury, the first professor of psychology distinct from philosophy at this university. They cover a variety of different topics including mysticism, the psychology of religion, and adolescence.
  - Advanced Social Psychology (Psychology 682)
    - Exams, 1967-1972 (Box 2)
    - Outlines, 1967-1972 (Box 2)
  - Attitudes and Behavior (Psychology 581), 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - General correspondence, 1977-1988 (Box 2)
  - Lecture Outlines (Handwritten notes), 1926-1952; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Seminar in Social Psychology (Psychology 782)
    - Exams, 1951-1973 (Box 2)
    - Outlines, 1957-1973 (Box 2)
  - Social Psychology (Psychology 681)
    - Exams, 1963-1966 (Box 2)
    - Outlines, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Statistics Cognate Requirements, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
- Sub-disciplines, 1969-1991
  The Sub-discipline series (3 linear feet, 1969-1991) consists of information relating to each separate course of study within the department. Documentation for each of these areas include committee minutes, correspondence, organizational information, reviews, and evaluations. The subdivisions seem to have acted as autonomous bodies within the department, making their own decisions regarding curriculum, enrollments, budget allocations, and other administrative activities. Larger administrative decisions were often made jointly with the executive committee (see Administrative Committees series for minutes). The sub-disciplinary areas for which the Bentley Historical Library holds materials are Applied, Clinical, Combined, Community, Developmental, Experimental, Mathematical, Organizational, Personality, Psychobiology, and Social Psychology. Materials are arranged into two sub-series: 1969-1985 and 1973-1991.
  - 1969-1985
    - Applied Psychology Area
      - General Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2)
      - Lab for Applied Psychology, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Clinical Area
      - Admissions Committee, 1970-1973 (Box 2)
      - Child Clinical Area, undated (Box 2)
      - Curriculum Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee (CAEC)
        - Accreditation, 1980 (Box 2)
        - Curricular Plan, 1980 (Box 2)
        - Doctoral Training Program, 1980 (Box 2)
        - Minutes
          - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
          - 1976 (Box 2)
          - 1977 (Box 2)
          - 1978 (Box 2)
          - 1979 (Box 2)
          - 1982 (Box 2)
          - 1983 (Box 2)
      - Field Placement Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
      - General Correspondence, 1969-1973 (Box 2)
      - Records and Evaluation Committee, 1977 (Box 2)
      - Reports, 1 folders
        - "Clinical Psychology at the University of Michigan--A Reexamination", 1967 (Box 2)
        - "APA Report for Approved Program in Clinical Psychology,", 1968-1969 (Box 2)
        - "Guidelines for Clinical Area Proposals for Programs of Advanced Study,", 1971 (Box 2)
        - "Proposed Modification of Diagnostic Assessment Sequence,", 1972 (Box 2)
        - "The Plan of Clinical Training at The U of M,", undated (Box 2)
      - Staff Meetings, 1972-1973; 1977-1978; 1982 (Box 2)
      - Undergraduate Committee, 1974 (Box 2)
      - Year End Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
    - Combined Program Area (Psychology and Education)
      - 1964-1973 (Box 2)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - 1976-1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Community Area
      - Correspondence, 1964-82 (Box 2)
      - History, 1971 (Box 2)
      - Minutes
        - 1971-1974 (Box 2)
        - 1975-1977 (Box 2)
    - Developmental Area, 1972-1975 (Box 3)
    - Experimental Area, 1967-1976 (Box 3)
    - Mathematical Area, 1972-1978 (Box 3)
    - Organizational Area, 5 folders
      - 1968-1969 (Box 3)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      - 1975-1977 (Box 3)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 3)
      - 1981-1984 (Box 3)
    - Personality Area, 1975-1980 (Box 3)
    - Psychobiology (Neuroscience), 1968-1976 (Box 3)
    - Social Psychology
      - Chairman Search, 1965 (Box 3)
      - Curriculum Committee, 1965 (Box 3)
      - Organization of Program in Social Psychology
        - 1961-1966 (Box 3)
        - 1967 (Box 3)
        - 1968 (Box 3)
        - 1969-1972 (Box 3)
  - 1973-1991
    - Biopsychology, 1982-1990 (Box 8)
    - Clinical Area
      - Chair, 1986 (Box 8)
      - Curriculum Committee, 1989 (Box 8)
      - Executive Committee Meetings, 1987-1990 (Box 8)
      - Faculty Meetings, 1985-1991 (Box 8)
      - Student Funding, 1987 (Box 8)
    - Clinical Psychology
      - Accreditation and Site Visit, 1985 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, 1982-1987 (Box 8)
      - Curriculum Review Committee Report, 1987 (Box 8)
      - Minority Recruitment Plan, 1984-1985 (Box 8)
      - Topics in Clinical Psychology, 1988 (Box 8)
    - Community Psychology, 1985 (Box 8)
    - Combined Program in Education and Psychology, 1981-1986; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Combined Program in Education and Psychology, 1981-1986; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Developmental Psychology
      - 1986-1991 (Box 9)
      - Newsletter, 1982-1989 (Box 9)
    - Organizational Psychology, 1982-1987; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Personality Psychology, 1973-1989 (Box 9)
    - Social Psychology, 1974-1990; 2 folders (Box 9)
- Topical Administrative Files, 1944-1997
  The Topical Administrative Files (2 linear feet, 1944-1997) is a correspondence file organized alphabetically by subject. These files are comprised of two sub-series: 1944-1985 and 1973-1991. It includes correspondence about such things as community and affiliated programs, minority students, and policy implementation. The topical file is scanty but does indicate the diversity of the programs and affiliations of the Department of Psychology both within the university and the Ann Arbor community in general.
  - 1944-1988
    - Affirmative Action, 1971-79 (Box 3)
    - American Psychological Association (APA) evaluations, 1975-81, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Animal Laboratories, 1962-69 (Box 3)
    - Black Psychologists, 1969-70 (Box 3)
    - Bureau of Psychological Services, 1949-1953; 1962-1963 (Box 3)
    - Center for Human Growth and Development, 1966-1971 (Box 3)
    - Center for Research on Conflict Resolution, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Corner House (554 Thompson Street), 1969-1976 (Box 3)
    - Counseling Program, 1976-1978 (Box 3)
    - Division of Gerontology, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Enrollment Statistics, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Evaluation and Examination Division, 1947-1949 (Box 3)
    - Institute of Human Adjustment, 1944-1966 (Box 3)
    - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities (ISSMRD), 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    - LSA Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
    - Programs in Clinical Psychology, 1945-1946 (Box 3)
    - Project Outreach, 1972-1977 (Box 3)
    - Psychological Clinic, 1954-1961 (Box 3)
    - Regents Fellowships, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Residential College, 1964-1967 (Box 3)
    - Student Statistical Breakdown, 1976-1988 (Box 3)
    - Technical Support, 1979-1987 (Box 3)
  - 1974-1997
    - Bush Program in Child Development and Social Psychology (Box 10)
      - 1977-1991 (Box 10)
    - Bush Program in Child Development and Social Psychology (cont.)
      - 1978-1984 (Box 10)
    - Center for the Study of Evolution and Human Behavior, 1990-1993 (Box 10)
    - Children's Center
      - Annual Report, 1984 (Box 10)
      - General, 1981-1989 (Box 10)
      - Newsletter, 1981-1989 (Box 10)
    - Center for Afro-American Studies, 1989-1991 (Box 10)
    - Cognitive Sciences and Machine Intelligence Laboratory, 1980-1990 (Box 10)
    - Cognitive Sciences and Machine Intelligence Laboratory Annual Report, 1981-1987 (Box 10)
    - Department of Psychiatry, 1982-1989 (Box 10)
    - Institute for Human Adjustment Transition Committee, 1986-1988 (Box 10)
    - Inteflex Program, 1974-1986 (Box 10)
    - Katz-Newcomb Symposium, 1997 (Box 10)
    - Kellogg Project, 1991; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Psychological Clinic, 1968-1991 (Box 10)
    - Psychology Teaching Institute
      - 1995-1996 (Box 10)
      - (Multicultural Institute), 1997 (Box 10)
    - Veteran's Administration, 1982-1989 (Box 10)
    - Women's Studies, 1990 (Box 10)
- Faculty, 1959-1989
  The Faculty series (0.5 linear feet, 1959-1989) includes materials related to the faculty and teaching assistants of the department such as information on salaries, work loads, appointments, candidate searches, tenures, and sabbaticals. It also documents university negotiations with teaching assistants and the Graduate Employees Organization.
  - General, 1979-1987 (Box 3)
  - Academic Staffing Priorities 1969-1972 Funding, 1976-1988 (Box 3)
  - Salaries, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Salaries, Women, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Search, Organizational Psychology, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Staff Work Load, 1959-1966 (Box 3)
  - Teaching Assistants (T.A.'s)
    - GEO, 2 folders
      - 1976 (Box 4)
      - 1985-1989 (Box 4)
    - Training, 1980-1989 (Box 4)
  - Visiting Faculty and Sabbaticals, 1984-1987 (Box 4)
  - Tenure, 1979-1980 (Box 4)
- Students, 1966-1988
  The Students series (0.25 linear feet, 1966-1988) consists of materials pertaining primarily to student concerns. While it is the smallest series it is interesting in that it represents the students themselves - a group that is often not reflected in the other materials.
  - Funding, 1987-1988
    - Student Grievances, 1976 (Box 5)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2051 ]
Related Material
For additional documentation of the activities of the University of Michigan's Department of Psychology see the collections of the faculty members: Clyde Coombs, Daniel Katz, E. Lowell Kelly, Richard Mann, Wilbert J. McKeachie, Theodore Newcomb, Walter Pillsbury, and the Shepard family, which includes lecture notes and notebooks of John F. Shepard, Professor of Psychology.
An unpublished history by Robert Pachella, "Creating the Modern Michigan Psychology Department: the Chairmanship of Donald Marquis (1945-1957)" details the dramatic post-World War II growth of the department. A copy of the history is available at the Bentley as well as online.